Guide to the George Parmly Day Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Parmly Day papers
1894-1960
MS 174
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(27 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence and other materials which relate to George Parmly Day's many positions at Yale University. The papers primarily concern Day's fund-raising activities as treasurer of the University and of the Alumni Fund and as secretary of the Class of 1897. To a lesser extent the papers reflect Day's publishing interests as a founder and director of the Yale University Press and contributor to the Yale Alumni Magazine. Included also are papers of the Acrotorque Company, a manufacturer of transmissions in Cleveland, Ohio.
Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George P. Day and others, ca. 1939-1982.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Letterpress Copybooks, 1908-1910. II. Correspondence, 1900-1960. III. Acrotorque Company Files, 1935-1947. IV. Personal Files, 1894-1956.
Scope and Contents
The George Parmly Day Papers consist of correspondence and other materials which document Day's long association with Yale University: as a member of the class of 1897; class secretary; founder and director of the Yale University Press; and as treasurer of the university and of the Yale Alumni Fund. The papers primarily concern Day's fund-raising activities but, to a lesser extent, reflect Day's publishing interests and his own writing. Also included in the papers are files of the Acrotorque Company, a manufacturer of transmissions in Cleveland, Ohio.
Some of the Day Papers were given to the Yale Library by George Parmly Day between 1939 and 1959. Other papers were gifts from associates or from offices in which Day had served, the most recent being a donation from the Yale Press in 1982. The Day Papers, while not a part of the Yale Archives, are closely related to official Yale business and contain papers kept by Day as treasurer and as president of Yale Press. Similar materials are found in the treasurer's records (YRG-5B), Alumni Fund records (YRG 7-B-2) and Yale University Press records (YRG 34-A). Additional Day papers, including some donated by George Parmly Day, are located in the Clarence Day Papers (MS 1094) and in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
The papers are arranged in four series: I. LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS, 1908-1910; II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1900-1960; III. ACROTORQUE COMPANY FILES, 1935-1947; IV. PERSONAL PAPERS, 1894-1956.
While the papers date from 1894 to 1960 the bulk of the material, which is contained in Series II, dates from 1939 to 1954.
Some of the earliest material is in boxes 1-3. Boxes 1 and 2 in Series I contain letterpress copies of Day's outgoing letters from 1908 to 1910. The incoming letter from 1910 are in box 3. Correspondents include Yale classmates, bankers, investors, and friends. The correspondence is personal and financial and a sizeable portion relates to the Yale University Press. Earlier letterbooks of the same character are found in YRG 34-A.
The remainder of Series II, CORRESPONDENCE, is arranged in sections: Yale University, divided further into General and Select, and General. These divisions of material represent an arrangement of files as they were received by the library. Items of the same correspondent may appear in all divisions and each division contains correspondence, minutes, reports, speeches, and printed matter, from the same general time period. George Parmly Day's role as a fund-raiser is the primary focus of all the material.
Material filed under Yale University: General (Boxes 4-5) represents occasional exchanges with many individuals. Folder 39 includes material on the Connecticut Association of the George Junior Republic, of which Day was president, while folder 35 contains letters of condolence on the death of Day's brother Clarence. Throughout there are letters from former Yale students who are serving or had served in World War I, as well as routine letters from Yale faculty, administration, and donors.
Much of the material filed under Yale University: Select (Boxes 6-13) concerns Yale funds and fund-raising. There are several folders concerning class gifts, memorials, and special campaigns filed under "Alumni Fund: General," as well as under names of fund officials such as: Edwin Blair, Edward J. Dimock, and William Ross Proctor, chairmen of the fund; and Curtis P. Fields, executive secretary. Papers containing discussions of donations and management of specific gifts are included in files for: Starling Childs, concerning the Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research; Theron Rockwell Field, Class of 1889 S Memorial Fund; Rebekah Kohut; Charles McC. Reeve; and the Lewis Baker Warren Foundation. Correspondence in the Arthur Bell, Thacher M. Brown, Class of '97, and Nathan Smyth files relates to fund raising from Day's Yale class of 1897 as well as class dinners, reunions, and support for classmates or their families. Folders 158-164 concern similar efforts by Day in behalf of the St. Paul's School Alumni Fund. Files for the Eno Foundation for Highway Traffic Regulation, which was affiliated with Yale and of which Day was treasurer contain by-laws, financial statements, and correspondence with Charles Tilden, Yale professor of engineering mechanics. More general discussions of Yale finance are contained in correspondence with Charles Seymour, Lawrence Tighe, and Wiggin and Dana. At the end of the section are folders relating to Yale Alumni Publications, Inc. including minutes of meetings, financial statements, and correspondence with Yale Press editor Francis W. Bronson.
The General files are similar in subject matter to the Yale University files, but contain papers after Day's various retirements in the early 1940s. The files contain a mixture of the occasional exchanges with individuals, which are filed in the alphabet files, and selected individual or topical files. There are many personal exchanges with Charles U. Clark, and folder 211 contains letter from Day's brother Julian describing life in war-torn Britain. The Friends of Music at Yale file contains minutes for this organization filed by Day as its treasurer; the New York Herald Tribune file concerns the publication of Day's "Ode to Miss Perkins"; and the Alumni Magazine files. (folders 297-298) 'incorporate Day's drafts for class notes. A series of strongly worded exchanges between Day and Charles Parsons is included in folder 260; more cordial exchanges with classmate Chauncey Goodrich concern Yale and fellow classmates. The file for Howell Wright exemplifies Day's concern and interests in the collections of the Yale Library.
Series III is composed of records of the Acrotorque Company of Cleveland, Ohio. How Day came into possession of these records is unclear. The records consist of reports, printed brochures, design specifications and studies, performance tests and data, photographs, and schematic drawings for the company's products, mainly hydraulic transmissions. Many of the reports are labelled as being the property of company vice president Elias Orshansky, Jr., a non-graduate of the Yale class of 1933.
Series IV includes a small quantity of Day's more personal papers. Folders 390-391 contain two volumes of Day's poetry: A Nonsense Book by & for and Rhymes of the Times. The series also includes photographs and a scrapbook begun by Day while he was a Yale undergraduate. The scrapbook is composed of Day's student essays, songs, and published writings, correspondence, clippings, and memorabilia such as invitations, menus, and programs for Yale events such as plays, class dinners, and fraternity meetings.
Biographical / Historical
George Parmly Day was born in 1876 and received a B.A. from Yale University in 1897. In 1907 Day organized the Yale Publishing Association, which became the Yale University Press in 1908. Day served as its president until 1944. In 1910 Day became treasurer of Yale and served as a successful fundraiser until 1942. He was one of four brothers described in his brother Clarence Day, Jr.'s Life With Father. George Parmly Day died in New Haven, Connecticut on October 24, 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Yale Alumni Magazine; Engineering; Fund raising; Hydraulic torque converters; Publishers and publishing; Mechanical drawings; Photoprints; Poems; Bell, Arthur T.; Blair, Edwin Foster, 1901-; Bronson, F. W. (Francis Woolsey), 1901-1966; Brown, Thatcher; Childs, Starling Winston, 1870-1946; Clark, Charles Upson, 1875-1960; Dana, Arnold Guyot, 1862-1947; Day, Clarence, 1874-1935; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Day, Julian; Dimock, Edward J.; Fields, Curtis P.; Goodrich, Chauncey William, 1864-1956; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Kohut, Rebekah Bettelheim, 1864-1951; Orshansky, Eli; Parsons, Charles, 1889-; Proctor, William Ross; Reeve, Charles McCormick, 1847-1947; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Tighe, Laurence G., 1894-1954; Wright, Howell, 1882-1954; Acrotorque Company; Eno Foundation for Highway Traffic Control; Yale Alumni Fund Association; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1897; Yale University Press; Yale University -- Finance; Yale University -- Funds and scholarships; Yale University -- Officals and employees
- LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS, 1908-1910; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1908 May-1910 April (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - 1910 May-August (Box 2, Folder 4-21)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1900-1960; Series II; 6.75; (18 boxes)
  This series is arranged in three sections: General, 1910; Yale University; and General.
  - General, 1910
    - A-Z, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 22-29)
  - Yale University
    - General, 1911-1939
      - A, 1919-1939 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Alexander, Ralph, 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - B, 1910-1939 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - C, 1913-1939 (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
      - D, 1919-1940 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Day, William E. family, 1911-1940 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - E-F, 1911-1940 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - G, 1934-1939 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - George Junior Republic Association, 1912-1915 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - H, 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 40-42)
      - J, 1918-1939 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - K, 1926-1939 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - L, 1900-1939 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - M, 1917-1939 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - N-R, 1918-1939 (Box 5, Folder 47)
        General
        See also: box 11, folder 149
      - S, 1918-1940 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
      - T, 1918-1940 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - U-V, 1918-1944 (Box 5, Folder 51)
        See also: box 12, folder 174
    - Select
      - Alumni Fund
        - General, 1939-1943 (Box 6, Folder 52-56)
        - Classes, 1928-1940 (Box 6, Folder 57-65)
        - Classes, 1940-1944 (Box 7, Folder 66-72)
        - Faculty, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 73)
        - In memoriam gifts, 1939-1943 (Box 7, Folder 74)
        - Special letters, 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 75-78)
      - Bell, Arthur, 1937-1944 (Box 7, Folder 79-81)
      - Blair, Edwin, 1941-1944 (Box 8, Folder 82-83)
      - Brown, Thatcher, 1931-1945, undated (Box 8, Folder 84-89)
      - Bunker, George Haring Memorial Fund, 1934-1945, undated (Box 8, Folder 90)
      - Callender, Walter R. (Mrs.), 1936-1939, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
      - Carey, Booth, 1938-1942 (Box 8, Folder 92-94)
      - Childs, Starling W., 1936-1944 (Box 8, Folder 95-99)
      - Class of '97, 1936-1945, undated (Box 9, Folder 100-107)
      - Commons, W. W., 1930-1931, undated (Box 9, Folder 108)
      - Cot, Pierre, 1939-1941 (Box 9, Folder 109)
      - Crosby, Raymond M., 1941-1942 (Box 9, Folder 110-111)
      - DeVane, William C., 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 112-113)
      - Dimock, Edward J., 1936-1940 (Box 9, Folder 114-115)
      - Drama, Department of, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 116)
      - Eno Foundation, 1920-1943, undated (Box 10, Folder 117-126)
      - Field, Theron Rockwell Class of 1889 Memorial Fund, 1943-1945, undated (Box 10, Folder 127-128)
      - Fields, Curtis P., 1939-1944, n.d (Box 10, Folder 129-131)
      - Flynn appointment, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 132)
      - Gilmore, Robert C., 1932-1942 (Box 10, Folder 133)
      - Goodrich, Chauncey W., 1938-1939 (Box 10, Folder 134)
        See also: box 16, folders 229-230
      - Gould, Lyttleton P., 1938-1939 (Box 10, Folder 134)
        See also: box 16, folder 231
      - Hewlett, Horace W., 1939-1941 (Box 10, Folder 135-136)
      - Hunt, Chester J., 1939-1945, undated (Box 11, Folder 137-142)
      - International relations, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 143)
      - Kohut, Rebekah, 1938-1945 (Box 11, Folder 144-146)
      - McCance, Chester, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Nyman, R. Carter, 1939-1943 (Box 11, Folder 148)
      - O, 1928-1943 (Box 11, Folder 149)
      - Phelps, William Lyon Memorial, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 150)
      - Phillips, Marion L., 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 151)
      - Reeve, Charles McC., 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 152-155)
        See also: box 18, folder 271
      - Proctor, William Ross, 1940-1943 (Box 11, Folder 156-157)
      - St. Paul's School Alumni Fund, 1941-1943, undated (Box 12, Folder 158-164)
      - Seymour, Charles, 1937-1945, undated (Box 12, Folder 165-166)
      - Smyth, Nathan A., 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 167)
      - Tighe, Laurence, 1939-1945 (Box 12, Folder 168-170)
      - Vermont, 1943-1945 (Box 12, Folder 171-173)
      - W, 1938-1945 (Box 12, Folder 174)
      - Wallingford House, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 175)
      - Washington and Lee University, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 176)
      - Warren, Lewis Baker Memorial Foundation, 1936-1941, undated (Box 12, Folder 177)
      - Weed, Eben, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 178)
      - Wiggin and Dana, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 179)
      - Wiggin and Dana, 1941-1944 (Box 13, Folder 180)
      - Wolf's Head property, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 181)
      - Wright, James, 1940-1943 (Box 13, Folder 182)
      - Yale Alumni Magazine, 1940-1945 (Box 13, Folder 183)
      - Yale Daily News, 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 184)
      - Yale Law School Association, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 185)
      - Yale Review, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 186)
      - Yale Publishing Association, Inc., 1907-1909 (Box 13, Folder 187-188)
      - Yale University Library, 1934-1945 (Box 13, Folder 189)
      - Yale University Press, 1938-1945 (Box 13, Folder 190)
  - General
    - A, 1936-1958 (Box 14, Folder 191-192)
    - Allen, Phillip R., 1940-1942 (Box 14, Folder 193)
    - Arkell, Bartlett, 1940-1943 (Box 14, Folder 194)
    - B, 1939-1958 (Box 14, Folder 195-197)
    - Benjamin, Judah P. Memorial, undated (Box 14, Folder 198)
    - Bennet, Wendell C. Memorial, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 199)
    - Bequest forms and pledges, undated (Box 14, Folder 200)
    - Brown, Gordon Prize, 1914-1947 (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - C, 1939-1958 (Box 14, Folder 202-206)
    - Clark, Charles U., 1941-1959 (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - Connfelt, Oscar G., 1940-1944 (Box 15, Folder 208)
    - Crosby, John, 1940-1944 (Box 15, Folder 209)
    - D, 1939-1959 (Box 15, Folder 210-211)
    - Dana, Arnold G., 1941-1945 (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - Dana, Richard H., 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 213)
    - Durant, Henry, 1936-1944 (Box 15, Folder 214)
    - Duryee, Samuel S., 1946-1948 (Box 15, Folder 215)
    - E, 1940-1954 (Box 15, Folder 216-217)
    - F, 1940-1958 (Box 15, Folder 218-220)
    - Farnam, Thomas W., 1940-1943 (Box 15, Folder 221)
    - Farwell, John V., 1940-1943 (Box 15, Folder 222)
    - Freshman inquiries, 1948-1957 (Box 15, Folder 223)
    - Friends of Music at Yale, 1953-1958 (Box 16, Folder 224)
    - G, 1936-1958 (Box 16, Folder 225-228)
    - Goodrich, Chauncey W., 1940-1956 (Box 16, Folder 229-230)
      See also: box 10, folder 134
    - Gould, Lyttleton P., 1940-1943 (Box 16, Folder 231)
    - Griswold, President A. Whitney, 1950-1957 (Box 16, Folder 232)
    - H, 1940-1958 (Box 16, Folder 233-236)
    - Honorary degrees, 1940-1950 (Box 16, Folder 237)
    - Howland, Frances L., 1940-1944 (Box 16, Folder 238)
    - I, 1940-1947 (Box 16, Folder 239-240)
    - J, 1940-1955 (Box 16, Folder 241-242)
    - K, 1939-1954 (Box 16, Folder 243-244)
    - L, 1937-1960 (Box 17, Folder 245-247)
    - Luce, Henry R., 1939-1943 (Box 17, Folder 248)
    - M, 1940-1958 (Box 17, Folder 249-253)
    - McKinistry, Helen, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 254)
    - Murphy, Fred T., 1940-1943 (Box 17, Folder 255)
    - N-O, 1936-1959 (Box 17, Folder 256-258)
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 259)
    - P, 1937-1958 (Box 17, Folder 260-261)
    - P-Q, 1939-1944 (Box 18, Folder 262)
    - Pierson College, 1946-1955 (Box 18, Folder 263-264)
    - R, 1939-1955 (Box 18, Folder 265-269)
    - Redlands, University of, [ca. 1948] (Box 18, Folder 270)
    - Reeve, Charles McC., 1940-1947 (Box 18, Folder 271)
      See also: box 11, folder 152-155
    - Ripley, Alfred L., 1938-1943 (Box 18, Folder 272)
    - S, 1928-1959 (Box 18, Folder 273-275)
    - Shaw, Ralph M., 1941-1945 (Box 18, Folder 276)
    - Spiegel, Hart Hunter, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 277)
    - T, 1939-1955 (Box 19, Folder 278-280)
    - Tamblyn and Brown, 1947-1951 (Box 19, Folder 281)
    - Thomas, Diana, 1940-1941 (Box 19, Folder 282)
    - Tomlinson, Carl P., 1944 (Box 19, Folder 283)
    - Treasurer's office, 1909, 1941-1950 (Box 19, Folder 284)
    - U-V, 1940-1958 (Box 19, Folder 285-287)
    - W, 1940-1958 (Box 19, Folder 288-291)
    - Wright, Howell, 1940-1943 (Box 19, Folder 292)
    - X-Z, 1945-1956 (Box 19, Folder 293)
    - Yale University
      - Alumni Fund Association
        - General, 1921, 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 294)
        - Bequest Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 19, Folder 295)
        - Resolution: GPD, 1951 (Box 19, Folder 296)
        - Alumni Magazine, 1942-1959 (Box 19, Folder 297-298)
      - Alumni University Fund, 1940-1945 (Box 20, Folder 299)
      - Medical unit, 1942 (Box 20, Folder 300)
      - University matters, 1911-1959 (Box 20, Folder 301)
      - Miscellany, 1914-1945 (Box 20, Folder 302)
- ACROTORQUE COMPANY FILES, 1935-1947; Series III; 2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
  This series is arranged by record type or topic.
  - Reports, 1935-1947 (Box 21, Folder 303-321)
  - Reports, 1935-1947 (Box 22, Folder 322-337)
  - Reports, 1935-1947 (Box 23, Folder 338-353)
  - Reports, 1935-1947 (Box 24, Folder 354-369)
  - Reports, 1935-1947 (Box 25, Folder 370-374)
  - Army specifications, 1939-1942 (Box 25, Folder 375-381)
  - Curtis Wright Corporation, 1945, undated (Box 25, Folder 382-387)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1894-1956; Series IV; 1.25 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - New Haven Committee of the British War Relief Society, Inc., 1940-1941 (Box 26, Folder 388)
  - Photographs (Box 26, Folder 389)
    See also: Oversize
  - Poetry, 1922, 1956 (Box 26, Folder 390-391)
  - Miscellanea, 1940, 1956, undated (Box 26, Folder 392)
  - Certificates and presentations
  - Miscellanea, undated (Box 26, Folder 392)
  - Scrapbook, 1894-1907 (Box 27, Folder 393)
- OVERSIZE
  - "George Parmly Day at 75", [1951] (Box 28)
  - Certificates and presentations, 1927-1951 (Box 28)
  - Photographs of B. H. Day, undated (Box 28)